The Adventures of Tom Sawyer by Mark
Twain to my wife this book is
affectionately dedicated preface most of
the adventures recorded in this book
really occurred one or two were
experiences my own the rest those of
boys who were schoolmates of mine Huck
Finn is drawn from life Tom Sawyer also
but not from an individual he is a
combination of the characteristics of
three boys whom I knew and therefore
belongs to the composite order of
architecture the odd superstitions
touched upon were all prevalent among
children and slaves in the West the
period of this story that is to say 30
or 40 years ago although my book is
intended mainly for the entertainment of
boys and girls I hope it will not be
shunned by men and women on that account
for a part of my plan has been to try to
pleasantly remind adults of what they
once were themselves and of how they
felt and thought and talked and what
queer enterprises they sometimes engaged
in the author Hartford 1876 chapter one
Tom no answer tom no answer what's gone
with that boy I wonder you Tom no answer
the old lady pulled her spectacles down
and looked over them about the room then
she put them up and looked out under
them she seldom or never looked through
them for so small a thing as a boy they
were her state pair the pride of her
heart and were built for style not
service she could have seen through a
pair of stove lids just as well she
looked perplexed for a moment and then
said not fiercely but still loud enough
for the furniture to hear well I lay if
I get hold of you I'll she did not
finish for by this time she was bending
down and punching under the bed with a
broom and so she needed breath to
punctuate the punches with she
resurrected nothing but the cat I never
see the beat of that
she went to the open door and stood in
it and looked out among the tomato vines
and jimpson weeds that constituted the
garden no Tom
so she lifted up her voice at an angle
calculated for distance and shouted you
Tom there was a slight noise behind her
and she turned just in time to seize a
small boy by the slack of his roundabout
and arrest his flight there I might have
thought of that closet what you've been
doing in there nothing nothing look at
your hands and look at your mouth
what is that truck I don't know what
well I know it's Jam that's what it is
40 times I've said if you didn't let
that Jam alone I'll skin you hand me
that switch the switch hovered in the
air the peril was desperate my look
behind you want the old lady whirled
round and snatched her skirts out of
danger the lad fled on the instant
scrambled up the high board fence and
disappeared over it his aunt polly's
stood surprised a moment and then broke
into a gentle laugh hang that boy can't
I never learn anything
ain't he played me tricks enough like
that for me to be looking out for him by
this time but old fools is the biggest
fools there is can't learn an old dog
new tricks as the saying is but my
goodness he never plays them alike two
days and how is a body to know what's
coming
he appears to know just how long he can
torment me before I get my dander up and
he knows if he can make out to put me
off for a minute or make me laugh it's
all down again and I can't hit him a
lick I ain't doing my duty by that boy
and that's the Lord's truth goodness
knows spare the rod and spoil the child
as the Good Book says I'm a laying up
sin and suffering a for us both I know
he's full of the old scratch but Laza me
he's my own dead sister's boy poor thing
and I ain't got the heart to lash him
somehow every time I let him off my
conscience does hurt me so and every
time I hit him my old heart most breaks
well well a man that is born of a woman
is a few days and full of trouble as the
scripture says and I reckon it's soul
he'll play hooky this evening that's
southwestern for afternoon' and I'll
just be obliged to make him work
tomorrow to punish him it's mighty hard
to make him work Saturdays when all the
boys is having holiday but he hates work
more than he hates anything else and I
have got to do some of my duty by him or
I'll be the ruination of the child Tom
did play hooky and he had a very good
time he got back home barely in season
to help Jim a small colored boy saw next
days would and split the kindling before
supper at least he was there in time to
tell his adventures to Jim while Jim did
three-fourths of the work Tom's younger
brother or rather half brother Sid was
already through with his part of the
work picking up chips for he was a quiet
boy and had no adventurous troublesome
ways while tom was eating his supper and
stealing sugar his opportunity offered
Aunt Polly asked him questions that were
full of guile and very deep for she
wanted to trap him into damaging
revealment like many others simple
hearted Souls it was her pet vanity to
believe she was endowed with a talent
for dark and mysterious diplomacy and
she loved to contemplate her most
transparent devices as marvels of low
cunning said she Tom it was middling
warm in school wasn't it yes'm powerful
warm wasn't it yes'm didn't you want to
go in a swimming Tom a bit of a scare
shot through Tom a touch of
uncomfortable suspicion he searched at
Polly's face but it told him nothing
so he said known well not very much the
old lady reached out her hand and felt
Tom's shirt and said but you ain't too
warm now though and it flattered her to
reflect that she had discovered that the
shirt was dry without anybody knowing
that that was what she had in her mind
but in spite of her Tom knew where the
wind lay now so he for stalled what
might be the next move some of us pumped
on our heads Minds damp yatshi' and
Polly was vexed to think she had
overlooked that bit of circumstantial
evidence and miss
the trick then she had a new inspiration
Tom you didn't have to undo your shirt
collar where I sewed it to pump on your
head did you unbutton your jacket the
trouble vanished out of Tom's face
he opened his jacket his shirt collar
was securely sewed bother well go along
with you I'd made sure you'd played
hooky and Benes women but I forgive you
Tom
I reckon you're a kind of singed cat as
the same is better than you look
this time she was how sorry her sagacity
had miscarried and half glad that Tom
had stumbled into obedient conduct for
once but Sydney said well now if I
didn't think you sewed his collar with
white thread but it's black why I did
sew it with white Tom but Tom did not
wait for the rest as he went out the
door he said city I'll lick you for that
in a safe place
Tom examined two large needles which
were thrust into the lapels of his
jacket and had thread bound about them
one needle carried white thread and the
other black he said she'd never noticed
if it hadn't been for CID confound it
sometimes she sews it with white and
sometimes she sews it with black I wish
to jiminy she'd stick to one or t'other
I can't keep the run of them but I bet I
learned to sit for that I'll learn him
he was not the model boy of the village
he knew the model boy very well though
and loathed him within two minutes or
even less he had forgotten all his
troubles now because his troubles were
one whit less heavy and bitter to him
than a man's are to a man but because a
new and powerful interest bore them down
and drove them out of his mind for the
time just as men's misfortunes are
forgotten in the excitement of new
enterprises this new interest was a
valued novelty in whistling which he had
just acquired from a Negro and he was
suffering to practice it undisturbed it
consisted in a peculiar bird-like turn a
sort of liquid warble produced by
touching the tongue to the roof of the
mouth at short intervals in the midst of
the music the reader probably remembers
how to do it if he has ever been a boy
diligence and a
tenshun soon gave him the knack of it
and he strode down the street with his
mouth full of harmony in his soul full
of gratitude he felt much as an
astronomer feels who has discovered a
new planet no doubt as far as strong
deep unalloyed pleasure is concerned the
advantage was with a boy not the
astronomer the summer evenings were long
it was not dark yet presently Tom
checked his whistle a stranger was
before him a boy a shade larger than
himself
a newcomer of any age or either sex was
an impressive curiosity in the poor
little shabby village of st. Petersburg
this boy was well dressed too
well-dressed on a weekday this was
simply astounding his cap was a dainty
thing his clothes buttoned blue cloth
roundabout was new and natty and so were
his pantaloons he had shoes on and it
was only Friday he even wore a necktie a
bright bit of ribbon he had acidified
air about him that ate into Tom's vitals
the more Tom stared at the splendid
marvel the higher he turned up his nose
at his finery and a shabbier and
shabbier his own outfit seemed to him to
grow neither boy spoke if one moved the
other moved but only sidewise in a
circle they kept face to face and eye to
eye all the time finally Tom said I can
lick you I'd like to see you try it well
I can do it no you can't either yes I
can no you can't I can you can't can't
can't an uncomfortable pause then Tom
said what's your name doesn't any your
business maybe well I'd allow I'll make
it my business well why don't you if you
say much I will much much much they are
now
oh you think you're mighty smart don't
you I could lick you with one hand tied
behind me if I wanted to well why don't
you do it you say you can do it well I
will if you fool with me oh yes I've
seen whole families in the same fix
smarty you think you're some now don't
you
oh what a hat you can lump that hat if
you don't like it I
dare you to knock it off and anybody
that will take a dare will suck eggs
you're a liar you're another you're a
fighting liar and doesn't take it up
take a walk say if you give me much more
of your sass I'll take and bounce a rock
off in your head oh of course you will
well I will well why don't you do it
then why do you keep saying you will for
why don't you do it it's because you're
afraid I ain't afraid you are I hate you
are another pause and more eying and
sideling around each other
presently they were shoulder to shoulder
tom said get away from me go away
yourself
I won't well I won't either so they
stood each with a foot placed at an
angle as a brace and both shoving with
might and main and glowering at each
other with hate but neither could get an
advantage after struggling till both
were hot and flushed each relaxed his
strain was watchful caution and Tom said
you're a coward and a pup I'll tell my
big brother on you and he can thrash you
with his little finger and I'll make him
do it too what do I care for your big
brother I've got a brother that's bigger
than he is and what's more he can throw
him over that fence too
both brothers were imaginary that's a
lie you're saying so doesn't make it so
Tom drew a line in the dust with his big
toe and said I dare you to step over
that and I'll lick you till you can't
stand up anybody that'll take a dare was
a steel sheep the new boy stepped over
promptly and said now you said you'd do
it now let's see you do it don't you
crowd me now you better look out well
you said you'd do it why don't you do it
by jingo for two cents I will do it the
new boy took two broad coppers out of
his pocket and held them out with
derision Tom struck them to the ground
in an instant both boys were rolling and
tumbling in the dirt gripped together
like cats and for the space of a minute
they tugged and tore at each other's
hair and clothes punched and scratched
each other's noses and covered
themselves with dust and glory presently
the confusion took form and through the
fog of battle Tom appeared
destryed the new boy and pounding him
with his fists holler enough said he the
boy only struggled to free himself he
was crying mainly from rage holler
enough and the pounding went on at last
the stranger got out of smothered nuff
and Tom let him up and said now that'll
learn you better look out who you're
fooling with next time the new boy went
off brushing the dust from his clothes
sobbing snuffling and occasionally
looking back and shaking his head and
threatening what he would do to Tom the
next time he caught him out to which Tom
responded with jeers and started off in
a high feather and as soon as his back
was turned the new boys snatched up a
stone through it and hit him between the
shoulders and then turned tail and ran
like an antelope Tom chased the traitor
home and thus found out where he lived
he then held a position at the gate for
some time daring the enemy to come
outside but the enemy only made faces at
him through the window and declined at
last the enemy's mother appeared and
called Tom a bad vicious vulgar child
and ordered him away so he went away but
he said he allowed to lay for that boy
he got home pretty late that night and
when he climbed cautiously in at the
window he uncovered an ambuscade in the
person of his aunt and when she saw the
state his clothes were in her resolution
to turn his Saturday holiday into
captivity at hard labor became
adamantine in its firmness in its
firmness nan its fur